<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="balisage-1-3.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="balisage-1-3.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0-subset Balisage-1.3">

    <title>Breaking <quote>Silo</quote> TEI to Make Interchangeable TEI</title>
    <subtitle>The Case of the Frankenstein Variorum Project</subtitle>
        <info>
          <abstract>
              <para></para>
          </abstract>  
          <author>
              <personname>
                  <firstname>Elisa</firstname>
                  <othername>Eileen</othername>
                  <surname>Beshero-Bondar</surname>
              </personname>
              <personblurb>
                  <para>Elisa Beshero-Bondar is a member of the TEI Technical Council, as well as an Associate Professor of English and Director of the Center for the Digital Text at the University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg. Her projects investigate complex texts such as epics, plays, and multi-volume voyage logs, and she is the founder and organizer of the <link xlink:href="http://digitalmitford.org">Digital Mitford project</link> and its annual coding school.</para>                 
              </personblurb>
              <affiliation>
                  <jobtitle>Associate Professor of English</jobtitle>
                  <jobtitle>Director, <link xlink:href="http://www.greensburg.pitt.edu/digital-humanities/center-digital-text">Center for the Digital Text</link></jobtitle>
                  <orgname>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</orgname>
              </affiliation>
              <email>ebb8@pitt.edu</email>
          </author>
            <author>
                <personname>
                    <firstname>Raffaele</firstname>
                    <surname>Viglianti</surname>
                </personname>
                <personblurb>
                    <para>Raffaele Viglianti is a TEI Technical Council member and Research Programmer at the Maryland Institute for Technology in the Humanities (MITH) at the University of Maryland, where he works on a number of digital humanities projects and is the Technical Editor for <link xlink:href="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/">the Shelley-Godwin Archive</link>. Raffaele’s research revolves around digital editions and textual scholarship, with a focus on editions of music scores.</para>
                </personblurb>
                <affiliation>
                    <jobtitle>Research Programmer</jobtitle>
                    <orgname>Maryland Institute for Technology in the Humanities (MITH) at the University of Maryland</orgname>
                </affiliation>
            </author>
            <keywordset role="author">
                <keyword>markup ecosystems</keyword>
                <keyword>interchange</keyword>
                <keyword>interchange format</keyword>
                <!--<keyword>early HTML</keyword>
                <keyword>hypertext edition</keyword>
                <keyword>web 1.0</keyword>-->
                <keyword>TEI P5</keyword>
                <keyword>collation</keyword>
                <keyword>Frankenstein</keyword>
                <keyword>Mary Shelley</keyword>
               <keyword>Bicentennial Frankenstein Project</keyword>
                <keyword>Frankenstein Variorum Edition</keyword>
                <keyword>variorum</keyword>
            </keywordset>
        </info>
    <section>
        <title>Building a Variorum Edition from Multiple Sources</title>
        <para>We aimed to improve the precision of the collation by processing with <link xlink:href="https://collatex.net">CollateX</link> software, which automates the location of alignments and deltas in multiple versions of a document. The document output by CollateX is plain text that holds critical apparatus tagging, and represents a first phase of up-translation to a new and improved TEI document. The next stage would be to apply auto-tagging with regular expressions to reconstruct the <quote>body</quote> of the edition in TEI as a single document from which multiple editions can be generated for reading and for genetic studying of textual variation over time.</para>
        <para> We would include pointers into <link xlink:href="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/contents/ms_abinger_c56/">the Shelley-Godwin Archive edition of the manuscript notebook drafts</link> of the novel.</para>
        
    </section>
    <section><title></title>
        <para></para>
    </section>
    <section><title></title>
        
   
        
               
        
        
        
        
    
    </section>

</article>
