<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="balisage-1-3.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="balisage-1-3.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0-subset Balisage-1.3">

    <title>Breaking <quote>Silo</quote> TEI to Make Interchangeable TEI</title>
    <subtitle>The Case of the Frankenstein Variorum Project</subtitle>
        <info>
          <abstract>
              <para></para>
          </abstract>  
          <author>
              <personname>
                  <firstname>Elisa</firstname>
                  <othername>Eileen</othername>
                  <surname>Beshero-Bondar</surname>
              </personname>
              <personblurb>
                  <para>Elisa Beshero-Bondar is a member of the TEI Technical Council, as well as an Associate Professor of English and Director of the Center for the Digital Text at the University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg. Her projects investigate complex texts such as epics, plays, and multi-volume voyage logs, and she is the founder and organizer of the <link xlink:href="http://digitalmitford.org">Digital Mitford project</link> and its annual coding school.</para>                 
              </personblurb>
              <affiliation>
                  <jobtitle>Associate Professor of English</jobtitle>
                  <jobtitle>Director, <link xlink:href="http://www.greensburg.pitt.edu/digital-humanities/center-digital-text">Center for the Digital Text</link></jobtitle>
                  <orgname>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</orgname>
              </affiliation>
              <email>ebb8@pitt.edu</email>
          </author>
            <author>
                <personname>
                    <firstname>Raffaele</firstname>
                    <surname>Viglianti</surname>
                </personname>
                <personblurb>
                    <para>Raffaele Viglianti is a TEI Technical Council member and Research Programmer at the Maryland Institute for Technology in the Humanities (MITH) at the University of Maryland, where he works on a number of digital humanities projects and is the Technical Editor for <link xlink:href="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/">the Shelley-Godwin Archive</link>. Raffaele’s research revolves around digital editions and textual scholarship, with a focus on editions of music scores.</para>
                </personblurb>
                <affiliation>
                    <jobtitle>Research Programmer</jobtitle>
                    <orgname>Maryland Institute for Technology in the Humanities (MITH) at the University of Maryland</orgname>
                </affiliation>
            </author>
            <keywordset role="author">
                <keyword>markup ecosystems</keyword>
                <keyword>interchange</keyword>
                <keyword>interchange format</keyword>
                <!--<keyword>early HTML</keyword>
                <keyword>hypertext edition</keyword>
                <keyword>web 1.0</keyword>-->
                <keyword>TEI P5</keyword>
                <keyword>collation</keyword>
                <keyword>Frankenstein</keyword>
                <keyword>Mary Shelley</keyword>
               <keyword>Bicentennial Frankenstein Project</keyword>
                <keyword>Frankenstein Variorum Edition</keyword>
                <keyword>variorum</keyword>
            </keywordset>
        </info>
    <section><title>TEI Ecosystems for Digital Editions: Why Can’t They Be Interoperable <emphasis>and</emphasis> Interchangeable?</title>
        <para>In her keynote address at the 2016 conference meeting of the Text Encoding Initiative in Vienna, Tara Andrews broached the issue of whether TEI can really be considered a <quote>de facto standard</quote> for the encoding and interchange of digital texts.<footnote><para>View Andrews’s keynote <link xlink:href="http://tei2016.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/keynote"><quote>Freeing Our Texts from their (Digital Tool)chains</quote></link>.</para></footnote> Her talk broached a long-recognized issue that the TEI Guidelines permit too many choices, so that for practical purposes there is very little that can be practically interoperable via simple programmatic mapping from one TEI project’s markup ecosystem to another. The TEI might well be a garden of too many forking paths, too richly labyrinthine because too entertaining of multiple modes of expression. Although Andrews’s talk specifically addressed the lack of interoperability in scholarly editions built with TEI and a consequent lack of available software tools to process all TEI documents, we might take this as a more fundamental concern that the TEI has not fulfilled a more basic promise of its origins. That is, beyond its difficulties in achieving interoperability, perhaps the Text Encoding Initiative as a wild ecosystem fails to live up to the ideal vaunted in the title of its documentation as <quote>Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange</quote>. Perhaps, too, it might be said that those of us who work with TEI do not sufficiently prioritize either interoperability or interchangeability in our projects. In the case study of the Frankenstein Variorum project presented in this paper, we exemplify and attempt to solve the problem of achieving interchangeability among different digital editions of a single literary work, by developing intermediary stand-off markup designed to <quote>bridge</quote> exceedingly different TEI markup ecosystems.</para>
        <para>Of course, to be <emphasis>interoperable</emphasis> is not the same thing as to be <emphasis>interchangeable</emphasis>. Syd Bauman’s definitive Balisage paper of 2011, <link xlink:href="https://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol7/html/Bauman01/BalisageVol7-Bauman01.html"><quote>Interchange vs. Interoperability</quote></link> is especially helpful in discussing and evaluating the different priorities represented by each term. Interoperability (or interoperationality) depends on whether a document can be processed by a computer program without human intervention. Interchangeability, on the other hand, involves human interpretation and is supported by community-defined vocabularies and well-written documentation. While TEI users often wish to prioritize ready interoperability, as in preparing <quote>Lite</quote> or <quote>Simple</quote> code easily interpretable by a software tool (say, a TEI plugin for a document viewer), Bauman finds that this is exceedingly difficult to achieve without sacrificing expressive semantics to the needs of a software package. By contrast, interchangeable encoding, especially encoding that permits what Bauman calls <quote>blind interchange</quote>, prioritizes human legibility, such that interpreting files does not require contacting the original encoder for help in understanding how the data was marked. Interchangeable data achieves semantic richness and lasting value without needing to predict the operating systems and software available to deliver it. It also does not require the forced simplification that interoperability demands for suiting what tools are or might become available.</para>
        <para>Bauman represents these goals as at odds with one another, stressing the point that interoperability is a matter of machine interpretation without human intervention: <quote>interoperability and expressiveness are competing goals constantly in tension with each other. While the analogy is far from exact, interoperationality is akin to equality, and expressiveness is akin to liberty.</quote> The equality Bauman ascribes to interoperable would seem to raze the complexity of a project, levelling all projects to simple terms common to a convenient universal application. Perhaps, though, enhancing the interchangeability of documents could create better conditions for interoperation that do not sacrifice the complex ontologies and research questions of data-driven TEI markup. Much depends on how we conceive of machine interoperation, our awareness of the suitability (and limits) of the tools we apply, and the constructions we develop to <quote>ramp up</quote> interchange.</para> 
        <para>Traditionally, TEI has supported both pursuits. As Elli Mylonas and Allen Renear discussed in 1999, TEI’s development of a language supporting data description and interchange supported an international research community as a tool of scholarship while also intervening in the <quote>proliferation of systems for representing textual material on computers. These systems were almost always incompatible, often poorly designed, and growing in number at nearly the same rapid rate as the electronic text projects themselves.</quote><footnote><para><link xlink:href="https://link.springer.com/content/pdf/10.1023%2FA%3A1001832310939.pdf">Elli Mylonas, Allen Renear, <quote>The Text Encoding Initiative at 10: Not Just an Interchange Format Anymore – But a New Research Community</quote> <emphasis>Computers and the Humanities</emphasis> 33:1-2 (April 1999) 1-9; 3.</link></para></footnote>.  </para>
        
   <para>
  
     
       <!--Syd uses the case of end-of-line soft vs. hard hyphenation as a serious issue of interoperability  -->
       <quote>The TEI currently (P5 v. 1.9.1) provides at least five different methods for encoding soft hyphens at end-of-line, three of which might use different characters for the representation of the hyphen itself (which is displayed as a hyphen (U+002D) in the listing below), and some previous releases of TEI allowed even more. This may strike some as silly or even excessive, but in most cases these choices make sense. For example, the TEI cannot prescribe to scholars who are not remotely interested in original lineation or soft hyphens that they record these features.</quote><quote>The good news is that TEI does actually provide a specific construct[6] for encoding how end-of-line hyphens are handled. The bad news is that the vocabulary available to describe the different encodings is insufficient to the task; furthermore, it is optional, and many, if not most, projects do not use it</quote>
       
   </para>
        <para><!--Why interchange is specifically important for collation.--></para>
    
    </section>
   
    
    
    <section>
        <title>Building a Variorum Edition from Multiple Sources</title>
        <para>We aimed to improve the precision of the collation by processing with <link xlink:href="https://collatex.net">CollateX</link> software, which automates the location of alignments and deltas in multiple versions of a document. The document output by CollateX is plain text that holds critical apparatus tagging, and represents a first phase of up-translation to a new and improved TEI document. The next stage would be to apply auto-tagging with regular expressions to reconstruct the <quote>body</quote> of the edition in TEI as a single document from which multiple editions can be generated for reading and for genetic studying of textual variation over time.</para>
        <para> We would include pointers into <link xlink:href="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/contents/ms_abinger_c56/">the Shelley-Godwin Archive edition of the manuscript notebook drafts</link> of the novel.</para>
        
    </section>
   
    <section><title></title>
      <para>CALL IT STAND-OFF PARALLEL SEGMENTATION</para>  
   
        
               
        
        
        
        
    
    </section>

</article>
