<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="balisage-1-3.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="balisage-1-3.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0-subset Balisage-1.3">

    <title>Standoff Bridges in the Frankenstein Variorum Project</title>
    <subtitle>Interchange and Interoperability within TEI Markup Ecosystems</subtitle>
    <info>
        <abstract>
            <para>Developing the Frankenstein Variorum Project has necessitated a reconciliation of
                extremely divergent markup ecosystems supporting multiple editions of a single
                novel. The reconciliation process involves breaking or flattening the original
                hierarchies to prioritize units of low-level lateral intersection, points shared in
                common to construct <quote>bridge</quote> or intermediary formats for processing
                with automated collation via collateX. The output from the automated collation
                process also serves as an intermediary format that we transform into a TEI form of
                    <emphasis role="ital">standoff parallel segmentation</emphasis>, in which
                standoff pointing mechanisms operate like a switchboard for connecting the
                individual editions which can remain (for the most part) undisturbed or unmarked
                from the collation process. The TEI <quote>standoff bridge</quote> negotiates the
                distinct markup ecosystems in ways that can break the <quote>silo</quote> effect of
                isolating specially encoded editions. Far from an ephemeral support structure, the
                standoff bridge upholds the whole as the <quote>backbone</quote> of the variorum
                project because it improves the interoperability and interchangeability of all the
                markup ecosystems involved. Building the standoff bridge effectively reconstitutes
                the hierarchies in a way that expresses intersections essentially as a graph
                structure of nodes with edge pointers to comparable nodes.</para>
            <para>Our experience on the Frankenstein Variorum is consistent with other TEI projects
                that involve curating divergence, variance, and forking in text streams. Taken
                together, such projects illuminate how the TEI can organize textual data in ways
                other than an ordered hierarchy of content objects, and that the TEI can be turned
                to express unordered <quote>lateral</quote> intersections in ways that serve
                long-standing goals of the TEI community: interchangeability and interoperability of
                electronic texts. As Syd Bauman in particular has discussed, where
                interchangeability reflects the capacity for humans to negotiate and adapt to markup
                ecosystems from systematic navigation and documentation without needing to contact
                the encoder for help, interoperability reflects the capacity of software tools to
                process the markup without needing to change the markup (or the tool). Although we
                usually consider the needs of software interoperability as at odds with the richly
                expressive capacity of human-readable semantic interchange, this paper demonstrates
                that the TEI can be designed to prioritize the interests of both, from facilitating
                automated collation to generating an interlinking web interface that gives the user
                means to choose and change directions in navigating multiple editions as
                desired.</para>
        </abstract>
        <author>
            <personname>
                <firstname>Elisa</firstname>
                <othername>Eileen</othername>
                <surname>Beshero-Bondar</surname>
            </personname>
            <personblurb>
                <para>Elisa Beshero-Bondar is a member of the TEI Technical Council, as well as an
                    Associate Professor of English and Director of the Center for the Digital Text
                    at the University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg. Her projects investigate complex
                    texts such as epics, plays, and multi-volume voyage logs, and she is the founder
                    and organizer of the <link xlink:href="http://digitalmitford.org">Digital
                        Mitford project</link> and its annual coding school.</para>
            </personblurb>
            <affiliation>
                <jobtitle>Associate Professor of English</jobtitle>
                <jobtitle>Director, <link
                        xlink:href="http://www.greensburg.pitt.edu/digital-humanities/center-digital-text"
                        >Center for the Digital Text</link></jobtitle>
                <orgname>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</orgname>
            </affiliation>
            <email>ebb8@pitt.edu</email>
        </author>
        <author>
            <personname>
                <firstname>Raffaele</firstname>
                <surname>Viglianti</surname>
            </personname>
            <personblurb>
                <para>Raffaele Viglianti is a TEI Technical Council member and Research Associate at
                    the Maryland Institute for Technology in the Humanities (MITH) at the University
                    of Maryland, where he works on a number of digital humanities projects and is
                    the Technical Editor for <link xlink:href="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/">the
                        Shelley-Godwin Archive</link>. Raffaele’s research revolves around digital
                    editions and textual scholarship, with a focus on editions of music
                    scores.</para>
            </personblurb>
            <affiliation>
                <jobtitle>Research Associate</jobtitle>
                <orgname>Maryland Institute for Technology in the Humanities (MITH) at the
                    University of Maryland</orgname>
            </affiliation>
        </author>
        <keywordset role="author">
            <keyword>markup ecosystems</keyword>
            <keyword>interchange</keyword>
            <keyword>interoperable</keyword>
            <keyword>interoperational</keyword>
            <keyword>intersectional</keyword>
            <keyword>interface</keyword>
            <keyword>OHCO</keyword>
            <keyword>hierarchy</keyword>
            <keyword>text stream</keyword>
            <keyword>forking</keyword>
            <keyword>divergence</keyword>
            <keyword>standoff</keyword>
            <keyword>graph</keyword>
            <keyword>graph model</keyword>
            <keyword>TEI P5</keyword>
            <keyword>collation</keyword>
            <keyword>variorum</keyword>
            <keyword>Frankenstein</keyword>
            <keyword>Mary Wollstonecraft Godwin Shelley</keyword>
            <keyword>Percy Bysshe Shelley</keyword>
            <keyword>Bicentennial Frankenstein Project</keyword>
            <keyword>Frankenstein Variorum Edition</keyword>
        </keywordset>
    </info>
    <section>
        <title>TEI Ecosystems for Digital Editions: Why Can’t They Be Interoperable <emphasis
                role="ital">and</emphasis> Interchangeable?</title>
        <para>In her keynote address at the 2016 conference meeting of the Text Encoding Initiative
            in Vienna, Tara Andrews broached the issue of whether TEI can really be considered a
                <quote>de facto standard</quote> for the encoding and interchange of digital texts.<footnote>
                <para>View Andrews’s keynote <link
                        xlink:href="http://tei2016.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/keynote"><quote>Freeing Our Texts
                            from their (Digital Tool)chains</quote></link>.</para>
            </footnote> Her talk broached a long-recognized issue that the TEI Guidelines permit too
            many choices, so that for practical purposes there is very little that can be
            practically interoperable via simple programmatic mapping from one TEI project’s markup
            ecosystem to another. The TEI might well be a garden of too many forking paths, too
            richly labyrinthine because too entertaining of multiple modes of expression. Although
            Andrews’s talk specifically addressed the lack of interoperability in scholarly editions
            built with TEI and a lack of available software tools to process universally all TEI
            documents, we might take this as a more fundamental concern that the TEI has not
            fulfilled a more basic promise of its origins. That is, beyond its difficulties in
            achieving interoperability, perhaps the Text Encoding Initiative as a wild ecosystem
            fails to live up to the ideal vaunted in the title of its documentation as
                <quote>Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange</quote>. Perhaps,
            too, it might be said that those of us who work with TEI do not sufficiently prioritize
            either interoperability or interchangeability in our projects. The goal of universal
            interoperation may simply be unrealistic for rich variety of applications employed
            around the world for the TEI, but interoperability among related kinds of documents
            would seem practically attainable. In the case study of the Frankenstein Variorum
            project presented in this paper, we exemplify and attempt to solve the problem of
            achieving interchangeability among different digital editions of the same novel in
            variant forms, by developing intermediary stand-off markup designed to
                <quote>bridge</quote> different TEI markup ecosystems with each their own priorities
            for description and representation of the novel.</para>
        <para>Of course, to be <emphasis role="ital">interoperable</emphasis> is not the same thing
            as to be <emphasis role="ital">interchangeable</emphasis>. Syd Bauman’s definitive
            Balisage paper of 2011, <link
                xlink:href="https://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol7/html/Bauman01/BalisageVol7-Bauman01.html"
                    ><quote>Interchange vs. Interoperability</quote></link> is especially helpful in
            discussing and evaluating the different priorities represented by each term.
            Interoperability (or interoperationality) depends on whether a document can be processed
            by a computer program without human intervention. Interchangeability, on the other hand,
            involves human interpretation and is supported by community-defined vocabularies and
            well-written documentation. While TEI users often wish to prioritize ready
            interoperability, as in preparing <quote>Lite</quote> or <quote>Simple</quote> code
            easily interpretable by a software tool (say, a TEI plugin for a document viewer),
            Bauman finds that this is exceedingly difficult to achieve without sacrificing
            expressive semantics to the requirements of a software package. By contrast,
            interchangeable encoding, especially encoding that permits what Bauman calls
                <quote>blind interchange</quote>, prioritizes human legibility such that
            interpreting files does not require contacting the original encoder for help in
            understanding how the data was marked. Interchangeable data achieves semantic richness
            and lasting value without needing to predict the operating systems and software
            available to deliver it. It also does not require the forced simplification that
            interoperability demands for suiting what tools are or might become available.</para>
        <para>Bauman represents these goals as at odds with one another, stressing the point that
            interoperability is a matter of machine interpretation without human intervention:
                <quote>interoperability and expressiveness are competing goals constantly in tension
                with each other. While the analogy is far from exact, interoperationality is akin to
                equality, and expressiveness is akin to liberty.</quote> The equality Bauman
            ascribes to interoperable would seem to raze the complexity of a project, levelling all
            projects to simple terms common to a convenient universal application. Perhaps, though,
            enhancing the interchangeability of documents could create better conditions for
            interoperation that do not sacrifice the complex ontologies and research questions of
            data-driven TEI markup. Much depends on how we conceive of machine interoperation, our
            awareness of the suitability (and limits) of the tools we apply, and the constructions
            we develop to <quote>cross-pollinate</quote> projects developed in distinct
            ecosystems.</para>
        <para>Traditionally, the TEI has cared about both ideals. As Elli Mylonas and Allen Renear
            discussed in 1999, TEI’s development of a language for data description and interchange
            helped to build and support an international research community with a tool for
            scholarship while also intervening in the <quote>proliferation of systems for
                representing textual material on computers. These systems were almost always
                incompatible, often poorly designed, and growing in number at nearly the same rapid
                rate as the electronic text projects themselves.</quote><footnote>
                <para><link
                        xlink:href="https://link.springer.com/content/pdf/10.1023%2FA%3A1001832310939.pdf"
                        >Elli Mylonas, Allen Renear, <quote>The Text Encoding Initiative at 10: Not
                            Just an Interchange Format Anymore – But a New Research
                            Community</quote> Computers and the Humanities 33:1-2 (April 1999) 1-9;
                        3.</link></para>
            </footnote>. While promoting blind interchange, TEI projects support development of
            specialized tools for constructing digital editions in particular, and of course this is
            where we run amok with the interoperability challenge. Optimally developers who work
            with TEI approach software tools with the caveat that some customization might be
            necessary to adapt the tool to respond to the distinctiveness of the data rather than
            the other way around, and that puts us into experimental territory as
                <quote>tinkerers</quote> or refiners of tools.</para>
        <para>In the history of preparing digital texts with markup languages, whether in early
            HTML, SGML, or XML, markup standards tensed between two poles: <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>the acknowledgement of a coexistence of multiple hierarchical structures,
                        and</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>the need to prioritize a single document hierarchy in the interests of
                        machine-readability, while permitting signposts of overlapping or
                        conflicting hierarchies as of secondary importance.<footnote>
                            <para>See for example, <link
                                    xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/4.2.99">P. M. W.
                                    Robinson, <quote>The Collation and Textual Criticism of
                                        Icelandic Manuscripts</quote>
                                    <emphasis role="ital">Literary and Linguistic
                                        Computing</emphasis>, Volume 4, Issue 2, 1 January 1989,
                                    99–105, https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/4.2.99</link>; <link
                                    xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqu007">Dekker, Ronald
                                    Haentjens, Dirk van Hulle, Gregor Middell, Vincent Neyt, and
                                    Joris van Zundert, <quote>Computer-supported collation of modern
                                        manuscripts: CollateX and the Beckett Digital Manuscript
                                        Project</quote>
                                    <emphasis role="ital">DSH: Digital Scholarship in the
                                        Humanities</emphasis> Volume 30, Issue 3, 1 September 2015,
                                    452–470, https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqu007</link>; <link
                                    xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqw043">Eggert, Paul,
                                        <quote>The reader-oriented scholarly edition</quote>
                                    <emphasis role="ital">Digital Scholarship in the
                                        Humanities</emphasis>, Volume 31, Issue 4, 1 December 2016,
                                    797–810, https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqw043</link>; and <link
                                    xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqw048">Holmes, Martin,
                                        <quote>Whatever happened to interchange?</quote>
                                    <emphasis role="ital">Digital Scholarship in the
                                        Humanities</emphasis>, Volume 32, Issue suppl_1, 1 April
                                    2017, 163–168, https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqw048</link>.</para>
                        </footnote></para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist> For us to write processes that <quote>read around</quote> conficting
            hierarchies, we require a third alternative that does not place coexistence in an
            oppositional camp, but rather prioritizes lateral intersections without sacrificing data
            curated in distinctly different structures. Makers of genetic editions (as for example
                <link xlink:href="http://beta.faustedition.net/">the genetic Faust edition</link>)
            find ourselves in this intermediary third position, when multiple encoding structures
            must co-exist and correlate to achieve a meaningful comparison of editions.<footnote>
                <para>See <link xlink:href="https://journals.openedition.org/jtei/697">Gerrit
                        Brüning, Katrin Henzel, and Dietmar Pravida, <quote>Multiple Encoding in
                            Genetic Editions: The Case of ‘Faust’</quote>, Journal of the Text
                        Encoding Initiative (4: March 2013).</link></para>
            </footnote> To produce an intermediating structure, the original hierarchies need to be
            reconceived in dynamic terms. We need to question and observe, where are their flex
            points for conversion from containment structures to loci of intersection? That, of
            course, is a determination reliant on interchange, in support of
            interoperationality.</para>
    </section>
    <section><title>Bridging the Isolated Ecosystems of Digital Frankenstein Editions to Collate Them</title>
        <para>We describe one such effort to support interchange and interoperability among multiple ecosystems we need to reconcile in the Frankenstein Variorum Project.<footnote><para>Our project, known variously as the Pittsburgh Frankenstein project but probably more aptly the Frankenstein Variorum project, involves a collaboration of researchers from the University of Pittsburgh, Carnegie Mellon University, and the Maryland Institute for Technology in the Humanities (MITH), and currently hosted at <link xlink:href="https://pghfrankenstein.github.io/Pittsburgh_Frankenstein/">https://pghfrankenstein.github.io/Pittsburgh_Frankenstein/</link>. At the time of this writing the web development for the variorum edition interface is under construction.</para></footnote> The effort involves preparing documents for processing with
                <link xlink:href="https://collatex.net">CollateX</link> software, which automates
            the location of alignments and deltas in multiple versions of a document. We prepared
            documents for collation that originated in different markup ecosystems, and we had to do
            the work of interchange. We had to develop an intermediary <quote>bridge format</quote>
            for all of our editions that exists specifically to serve the operational purpose of
            collation, that is, the marking of moments of divergence and variation in comparable
            units of text that processes <emphasis role="ital">only</emphasis> what is semantically
            comparable (including the words in the novel, and whether they are marked for insertion
            or deletion) and masks or ignores the portions of the documents that are not relevant
            for comparison purposes (including for our purposes the elements indicating pagination
            and location on a page surface). Here is a sample of the most elaborately marked TEI we
            have, from the Shelley-Godwin Archive:</para>
        <programlisting>
                 &lt;zone type="main"&gt;
    &lt;line rend="center"&gt;&lt;milestone spanTo="#c56-0045.04" unit="tei:head"/&gt;Chapter 7&lt;hi rend="sup"&gt;&lt;hi rend="underline"&gt;th&lt;/hi&gt;&lt;/hi&gt;&lt;anchor xml:id="c56-0045.04"&gt;&lt;/anchor&gt;&lt;/line&gt;
    &lt;milestone unit="tei:p"&gt;&lt;/milestone&gt;
    &lt;line rend="indent1"&gt;It was on a dreary night of November&lt;/line&gt;
    &lt;line&gt;that I beheld &lt;del rend="strikethrough"&gt;&lt;add hand="#pbs" place="superlinear"&gt;the frame on
          whic&lt;/add&gt;&lt;/del&gt; my man comple&lt;mod&gt;
        &lt;del rend="overwritten"&gt;at&lt;/del&gt;
        &lt;add place="intralinear"&gt;te&lt;/add&gt;
        &lt;add&gt;ed&lt;/add&gt;
      &lt;/mod&gt;&lt;add hand="#pbs" place="intralinear"&gt;,&lt;/add&gt;. &lt;del rend="strikethrough"&gt;And&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/line&gt;
    &lt;line&gt;with an anxiety that almost amount&lt;/line&gt;
    &lt;line&gt;ed to agony I collected instruments of life&lt;/line&gt;
    &lt;line&gt;around me &lt;mod&gt;
        &lt;del rend="strikethrough"&gt;and endeavour to&lt;/del&gt;
        &lt;add place="superlinear"&gt;that I might&lt;/add&gt;
      &lt;/mod&gt;
      &lt;mod&gt;
        &lt;del rend="overwritten"&gt;e&lt;/del&gt;
        &lt;add place="intralinear"&gt;i&lt;/add&gt;
      &lt;/mod&gt;nfuse a&lt;/line&gt;
    &lt;line&gt;spark of being into the lifeless thin&lt;mod&gt;
        &lt;del rend="overwritten"&gt;k&lt;/del&gt;
        &lt;add place="intralinear"&gt;g&lt;/add&gt;
      &lt;/mod&gt;&lt;/line&gt;
    &lt;line&gt;that lay at my feet. It was already&lt;/line&gt;
    &lt;line&gt;one in the morning, the rain pattered&lt;/line&gt;
    &lt;line&gt;dismally against the window panes, &amp;&lt;/line&gt;
    &lt;line&gt;my candle was nearly burnt out, when&lt;/line&gt;
    &lt;line&gt;by the glimmer of the half extinguish-&lt;/line&gt;
    &lt;line&gt;ed light I saw the dull yellow eye of&lt;/line&gt;
    &lt;line&gt;the creature open.—It breathed hard,&lt;/line&gt;
    &lt;line&gt;and a convulsive motion agitated&lt;/line&gt;
    &lt;line&gt;its limbs.&lt;/line&gt;
    &lt;milestone unit="tei:p"/&gt;
    ...
    &lt;/zone&gt;
            </programlisting>
        <para>The markup above prioritizes description of lines on a manuscript notebook page
            surface, delineated in a zone element, and the line elements together with those
            indicating insertions and deletions pose us an obstacle course if we wish to attempt to
            compare this passage with its corresponding unit in the much simpler XML encoding we
            prepared for the print publications. One significant problem that we needed to solve is the way words break around
            the ends of lines in the notebooks. These are given hyphens only when present in the
            manuscript and are otherwise unmarked. Consider the challenge of comparing the sequential stream of text delineated in the code block above with the corresponding passage in our XML encoding of the 1818 edition:
            <programlisting>              
      &lt;xml&gt;
   &lt;anchor type="collate" xml:id="C10"/&gt;
   &lt;milestone unit="chapter" type="start" n="4"/&gt;
   &lt;head&gt;CHAPTER IV.&lt;/head&gt;
   &lt;p&gt;I&lt;hi rend="smallcaps"&gt;T&lt;/hi&gt; was on a dreary night of November, that I beheld the
            accomplishment of my toils. With an anxiety that almost amounted to agony, I collected
            the instruments of life around me, that I might infuse a spark of being into the
            lifeless thing that lay at my feet. It was already one in the morning; the rain pattered
            dismally against the panes, and my candle was nearly burnt out, when, by the glimmer of
            the half-extinguished light, I saw the dull yellow eye of the creature open; it breathed
              &lt;pb xml:id="F1818_v1_110" n="098"/&gt;hard, and a convulsive motion agitated its
            limbs.&lt;/p&gt;
...
      &lt;/xml&gt;
  </programlisting>
            Note: the code above for the pre-collation version of the 1818 edition is not written in
            TEI, but borrows its elements. This is an example of simple XML we prepared specifically
            for the purpose of collation, reducing the documents to concentrate on the
                <quote>running stream</quote> of text and its basic structural divisions. Here the
            paragraph is the most basic structural division, and chapter boundaries are signalled
            with milestone markers.</para>
        <para>The act of reconciling these markup ecosystems required altering the structure of the
            S-GA markup, to produce it in an alternative pre-collation <quote>bridge</quote> format
            that matches up with elements in the encoding of the published editions, which in this
            paper we will simply call <quote>1818-style</quote>). In the S-GA markup the hierarchy
            is not especially deep, or it only becomes deep in describing revision activities and
            changes of hand. These hierarchical structures do not correspond with anything in the
            markup of the print-published editions, where hierarchical depth comes from chapter,
            letter, and volume divisions. To make a collatable <quote>bridge</quote> format required
            alteration of each (S-GA and 1818-style) to <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><quote>meet in the middle</quote>: share matching elements that contain
                        and signal the sequence of text to be collated, and</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><quote>stay apart</quote>: preserve the diversity of metadata in the S-GA
                        markup about revisions and handshifts, and find a way to ignore or mask it
                        from the collation process.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist> To build the <quote>pre-collation bridge formats</quote>, we needed to
            flatten deep hierarchical structures from the <quote>1818-style</quote> XML documents by
            converting them into milestone-style signals. We want to retain the information about
            structural divisions, that is, paragraph, chapter, letter, and volume boundaries, and
            include this as data, since changes in paragraphing or chapter content are relevant to
            the variorum comparison of the Frankenstein editions. However, we also retain markup
            which does not designate the running sequence of text and basic text structure, but
            offers metadata about who wrote what, and whether the writing was inserted or deleted.
            This allows us to reconcile hierarchies that are otherwise completely at odds and
            nevertheless preserve their information, though we need to do another round of work to
            screen some of that information away from the collation process. Below is the sample
            passage from the Shelley-Godwin Notebooks rendered in our bridge format, designed to be
            comparable laterally with corresponding encoding in the 1818-style that we represented
            in the block above.
            <programlisting>
            &lt;xml&gt;
   &lt;anchor type="collate" xml:id="C10"/&gt;
   &lt;surface xmlns:mith="http://mith.umd.edu/sc/ns1#"
            lrx="3847"
            lry="5342"
            partOf="#ox-frankenstein_volume_i"
            ulx="0"
            uly="0"
            mith:folio="21r"
            mith:shelfmark="MS. Abinger c. 56"
            xml:base="ox-ms_abinger_c56/ox-ms_abinger_c56-0045.xml"
            xml:id="ox-ms_abinger_c56-0045"&gt;
      &lt;graphic url="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/images/ox/ms_abinger_c56/ms_abinger_c56-0045.jp2"/&gt;
      &lt;zone type="main"&gt; 
         &lt;lb n="c56-0045__main__1"/&gt;
         &lt;milestone spanTo="#c56-0045.04" unit="tei:head"/&gt;Chapter 7&lt;hi rend="sup"&gt;
            &lt;hi rend="underline"&gt;th&lt;/hi&gt;
         &lt;/hi&gt;
         &lt;anchor xml:id="c56-0045.04"/&gt;
         &lt;milestone unit="tei:p"/&gt; 
         &lt;lb n="c56-0045__main__2"/&gt;It was on a dreary night of November &lt;lb n="c56-0045__main__3"/&gt;that I beheld &lt;del rend="strikethrough"&gt;
            &lt;add hand="#pbs" place="superlinear"&gt;the frame on
          whic&lt;/add&gt;
         &lt;/del&gt; my man comple&lt;mod&gt;
        
            &lt;add place="intralinear"&gt;te&lt;/add&gt;
            &lt;add&gt;ed&lt;/add&gt;
         &lt;/mod&gt;
         &lt;add hand="#pbs" place="intralinear"&gt;,&lt;/add&gt;. &lt;del rend="strikethrough"&gt;And&lt;/del&gt; 
         &lt;lb n="c56-0045__main__4"/&gt;with an anxiety that almost 
         &lt;w ana="start"/&gt;amount&lt;lb n="c56-0045__main__5"/&gt;ed&lt;w ana="end"/&gt; to agony I 
         collected instruments of life 
         &lt;lb n="c56-0045__main__6"/&gt;around me &lt;mod&gt;
            &lt;del rend="strikethrough"&gt;and endeavour to&lt;/del&gt;
            &lt;add place="superlinear"&gt;that I might&lt;/add&gt;
         &lt;/mod&gt;
         &lt;mod&gt;
        
            &lt;add place="intralinear"&gt;i&lt;/add&gt;
         &lt;/mod&gt;nfuse a &lt;lb n="c56-0045__main__7"/&gt;spark of being into the lifeless thin&lt;mod&gt;
        
            &lt;add place="intralinear"&gt;g&lt;/add&gt;
         &lt;/mod&gt; 
         &lt;lb n="c56-0045__main__8"/&gt;that lay at my feet. It was already 
         &lt;lb n="c56-0045__main__9"/&gt;one in the morning, the rain pattered 
         &lt;lb n="c56-0045__main__10"/&gt;dismally against the window panes, &amp; 
         &lt;lb n="c56-0045__main__11"/&gt;my candle was nearly burnt out, when 
         &lt;lb n="c56-0045__main__12"/&gt;by the glimmer of the half 
         &lt;w ana="start"/&gt;extinguish&lt;lb n="c56-0045__main__13"/&gt;ed&lt;w ana="end"/&gt; 
         light I saw the dull yellow eye of &lt;lb n="c56-0045__main__14"/&gt;the creature open.—It breathed hard, 
         &lt;lb n="c56-0045__main__15"/&gt;and a convulsive motion agitated 
         &lt;lb n="c56-0045__main__16"/&gt;its limbs.&lt;milestone unit="tei:p"/&gt;    
        </programlisting>
            Notice what has changed here: We not only had to flatten <code>&lt;line&gt;</code>
            elements into self-closing <code>&lt;lb/&gt;</code> signals but we needed to actively
            insert <code>&lt;word&gt;</code> elements to unite whole words broken around the
            notebook lines. We also added locational <quote>flags</quote> or <quote>signal
                beacons</quote> as the attribute on <code>&lt;lb n="*"/&gt;</code>, to assist us on
            the other side of the collation with generating XML pointers back to the source text:
            these indicate positional zones and lines on the notebook page surfaces, so that when
            output that data can be kept with its associated collation units. In these
            information-enriching activities, of course, we are doing the human work required of
            interchange, and we do so in the interests of interoperability, so the automated
            collation process can locate the same word tokens without interference.</para>
        <para> The <quote>pre-collation bridge format</quote> needs to retain certain marked metadata from the
            original TEI, including for example, whose hands are at work on the manuscript at a
            given moment, so we can attempt to see if a string of text inserted by Percy Bysshe
            Shelley continues to be supported in the later print publications. However, such
            metadata needs to be masked from the collation process so that we are not folding it
            into comparison of the running streams of text that compose each version of the novel.
            To deliver these <quote>pre-collation bridge</quote> XML files to collateX and instruct
            the software collation algorithm on how to process them, <emphasis role="ital"
                >with</emphasis> and <emphasis role="ital">around</emphasis> their markup, we wrote
            a Python script working with its xml.dom.pulldom tool, which parses XML documents as a running stream of text and instructs the collation process to ignore some
            patterns surrounded by angle brackets, while actively collating the others.<footnote><para>See the xml.dom.pulldom documentation here: <link xlink:href="https://docs.python.org/3/library/xml.dom.pulldom.html">https://docs.python.org/3/library/xml.dom.pulldom.html</link>. The Python script is available on our GitHub repository here: <link xlink:href="https://github.com/PghFrankenstein/Pittsburgh_Frankenstein/blob/master/collateXPrep/allWitness_collation_to_tei.py">https://github.com/PghFrankenstein/Pittsburgh_Frankenstein/blob/master/collateXPrep/allWitness_collation_to_tei.py</link>.</para></footnote>
      
        
        </para>
        <para>In turn, the XML output generated by collateX, too, serves as an intermediary format,
            not in TEI, but containing its components in the form of critical apparatus tagging, to
            hold information about the deltas of variance among the editions. Here is a screen capture of the collation output for the sample portion of <emphasis role="ital">Frankenstein</emphasis> we have been representing: 
    
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata format="png" fileref="Bal2018collateOutput042908.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
            
            Pulling from this <quote>pre-TEI</quote> output from
            the collation process, we then apply XSLT to build the TEI <quote>spinal column</quote>
            of our Variorum edition, an edition that applies stand-off pointers in a new method we
            are calling <quote>stand-off parallel segmentation</quote>. Our method enhances the
            available models in the TEI for stand-off collation, while supporting the TEI’s
            longstanding interests in both interchange and interoperability. We want to promote the
            long-term sustenance of digital editions by actively building bridges to render isolated
            monumental projects interchangeable rather than remake them from the ground up. Building
            ramps for interchangeability is an investment in interoperability as well, specifically
            for producing the comparative views afforded by collation.</para>
        <para>Though we confine our case-study for this paper to the automated collation process and
            what we can build for it and from it, the perspective on enhancing interchange for the
            purposes of interoperation has larger ramifications in the ongoing discussion of
            graph-based models and their application to the TEI.<footnote>
                <para>For reflection on pertinent examples, see Hugh A. Cayless, <link
                        xlink:href="http://journals.openedition.org/jtei/907"><quote>Rebooting TEI
                            Pointers</quote>, Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative, Issue 6,
                        December 2013</link> and his blog posting, <link
                        xlink:href="https://blogs.library.duke.edu/dcthree/2013/08/26/graphs-trees-and-streams-the-tei-data-model/"
                            ><quote>Graphs, Trees, and Streams: The TEI Data Model</quote>, Duke
                        Collaboratory for Classics Computing (DC3), 26 August 2013</link>. Cayless’s
                    work on developing pointer specifications to enhance TEI expression beyond
                    inline embedded markup is now part of the <link
                        xlink:href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/SA.html#SATS"
                        >TEI Guidelines Chapter 16: Linking, Segmentation, and Alignment</link>,
                        <link
                        xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol5/html/Cayless01/BalisageVol5-Cayless01.html"
                        >Cayless, Hugh A., and Adam Soroka. “On Implementing string-range() for
                        TEI.” Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2010. Balisage Series
                        on Markup Technologies, vol. 5 (2010)</link>.</para>
            </footnote> For much the same reasons that motivate us, Jeffrey C. Witt designed the
            Scholarly Commentaries and Texts Archive, to transform digital <quote>silo</quote>
            projects into a network of data and while that project seeks a definitive language of
            interchange for medieval scholastic textual data, on a smaller scale trained on multiple
            divergent encodings of the same famous novel, we have negotiated interchangeability by
            cutting across individual text hierarchies to emphasize lateral connections and
            commonalities—making a new TEI whose hierarchy serves as a stand-off
                <quote>backbone</quote> or <quote>switchboard</quote> permitting comparison and
            sharing of common data.<footnote>
                <para><link
                        xlink:href="https://www.helsinki.fi/en/unitube/video/c7b16d35-dd91-419b-b017-a4a8373eac63"
                        >See Jeffrey C. Witt’s recorded presentation, <quote>Texts as Networks: The
                            Promise and Challenge of Publishing Humanities Texts as Open Data
                            Networks</quote> for the Conference on Philosophy and History of Open
                        Science at the University of Helsinki, 30 November - 1 December 2016</link>,
                    and on better supporting interoperability in particular see his <link
                        xlink:href="http://lombardpress.org/2016/08/25/basel-workshop-report/"
                            ><quote>Creating an aggregated dataset from distributed
                        sources</quote></link>, a report from the <quote>Linked Data and the
                        Medieval Scholastic Tradition</quote> workshop held at the University of
                    Basel in August 17-19, 2016.</para>
            </footnote></para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Building a Variorum Edition from Multiple Sources</title>
        <para>In the process of collation, hierarchies must be dismantled and flattened in order for
            meaningful multiplicity to be represented, and in order for us to understand a dialogic
            relationship among textual variants. To study variation over time vexes the organizing
            principle of any singular hierarchy, but for an alternative bridge-building
            architecture, arches and connecting spans are more viable than monoliths. Our use of the
            terms <quote>arch</quote>, <quote>bridge</quote>, or <quote>span</quote> is more than a
            metaphor here, but drawn from a graph-based model of text on which, not coincidentally,
            collateX was designed for locating variants in documents. <footnote>
                <para>See the documentation, <link xlink:href="https://collatex.net/doc/"
                            ><quote>CollateX – Software for Collating Textual
                    Sources</quote></link>. Another inspiration for the bridging concept are the
                    visualizations in <link
                        xlink:href="https://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol19/html/Dekker01/BalisageVol19-Dekker01.html#d11284e1180"
                        >Haentjens Dekker, Ronald, and David J. Birnbaum. “It’s more than just
                        overlap: Text As Graph.” In <emphasis role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage:
                            The Markup Conference 2017. Balisage Series on Markup
                            Technologies</emphasis>, vol. 19 (2017).</link>. The authors
                    conceptualize an ideal model of texts in a graph structure organized primarily
                    by their semantic sequencing and in which structural features are a matter of
                    descriptive annotation rather than elemental hierarchy.</para>
            </footnote></para>

        <para>We have had to contend with the challenge of collating digital editions made at
            different times by different editors in order to prepare a variorum edition of
            Frankenstein in TEI P5. Our collation source documents are adapted from the 1990s web
            1.0 HTML encoding of the Pennsylvania Electronic Edition of <emphasis role="ital"
                >Frankenstein</emphasis> for the 1818 and 1831 editions<footnote>
                <para>Curran, Stuart and Jack Lynch. <link
                        xlink:href="http://knarf.english.upenn.edu/">Frankenstein; or, the Modern
                        Prometheus. The Pennsylvania Electronic Edition</link>. Est. 1994. See a
                    representative page at <link
                        xlink:href="http://knarf.english.upenn.edu/Colv1/f1101.html"
                        >http://knarf.english.upenn.edu/Colv1/f1101.html</link>.</para>
            </footnote>, and the Shelley-Godwin Archive’s diplomatic edition of the manuscript
            notebooks of 1816, the only known existing drafts of the novel.<footnote>
                <para>The Shelley-Godwin Archive's edition of the manuscript notebooks of
                    Frankenstein builds on decades of intensive scholarly research to create TEI
                    diplomatic encoding: <link
                        xlink:href="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/contents/frankenstein/"
                        >http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/contents/frankenstein</link>/. </para>
            </footnote> We are also newly incorporating a little-known edition of the novel’s 1823
            publication produced from corrected OCR of a Google Books facsimile, together with
            transcription of Mary Shelley’s handwritten revision notes on a copy of the 1818
            publication known as <quote>the Thomas copy</quote> held at the Morgan Library and
            Museum. Our collation should yield a meta-narrative of how <emphasis role="ital"
                >Frankenstein</emphasis> changed over time in four versions that passed through
            multiple editorial hands. It is widely understood that the 1831 edition diverges sharply
            from the first print edition of 1818, adding new material and changing the relationships
            of characters. Less known is how the notebook material compares with the print editions,
            and how much we can identify of the persistence of various hands involved in composing,
            amending, and substantially revising the novel over the three editions. For example, to
            build on Charlie Robinson’s identification of Percy Bysshe Shelley’s hand in the
            notebooks, our collation can reveal how much of Percy’s insertions and deletions survive
            in the later print editions. Our work should permit us to survey when and how the major
            changes of the 1831 text (for example, to Victor Frankenstein’s family members and the
            compression and reduction of a chapter in part I) occurred. We preserve information
            about hands, insertions, and deletions in the output collation, to serve as the basis
            for better quantifying, characterizing, and surveying the contexts of collaboration and
            revision in textual scholarship.</para>

        <para>The three print editions and extant material from three manuscripts are compared in
            parallel, to indicate the presence of variants in the other texts and to be able to
            highlight them based on intensity of variance, to be displayed like the highlighted
            passages in each visible edition of <emphasis role="ital">The Origin of
                Species</emphasis> in Darwin Online.<footnote>
                <para>Barbara Bordalejo, ed. Darwin Online. See for example the illumination of
                    variant passages in The Origin of Species here: <link
                        xlink:href="http://darwin-online.org.uk/Variorum/1859/1859-1-dns.html"
                        >http://darwin-online.org.uk/Variorum/1859/1859-1-dns.html</link></para>
            </footnote> Rather than any edition serving as the lemma or grounds for collation
            comparison, we hold the collation information in stand-off markup, in its own XML
            hierarchy. That XML <quote>bridge</quote> expresses relationships among the distinct
            encodings of diplomatic manuscript markup in which the highest level of hierarchy is a
            unit leaf of the notebook, with the structural encoding of print editions organized in
            chapters, letters, and volumes. While the apparently nested structure of these divisions
            might seem the most meaningful way to model <emphasis role="ital"
                >Frankenstein</emphasis>, these pose a challenge to textual scholarship in their own
            right. As Wendell Piez has discussed, <emphasis role="ital">Frankenstein</emphasis>’s
            overlapping hierarchies of framing letters and chapters have led to inconsistencies in
            the novel's print production. Piez deploys a non-hierarchical encoding of the novel on
            which he constructs an SVG modeling (in ordered XML syntax) of the overlap itself.<footnote>
                <para>These hierarchical issues provided an application for Piez’s invented LMNL
                        <quote>sawtooth</quote> syntax to highlight overlap as semantically
                    important to the novel; see <link
                        xlink:href="https://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol13/html/Piez01/BalisageVol13-Piez01.html"
                        >Wendell Piez, <quote>Hierarchies within range space: From LMNL to
                            OHCO</quote> Balisage: The Markup Conference Proceedings (2014):
                        https://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol13/html/Piez01/BalisageVol13-Piez01.html</link>
                </para>
            </footnote> Our work with collation depends on a similar interdependency of structurally
            inconsistent encoding.</para>

        <para>Our method involves three stages of structural transformation, each of which disrupts
            the hierarchies of its source documents: <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Preparing texts for collation with CollateX,</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Collating a new "braided" structure in CollateX XML output, which
                        positions each variant in its own reading witness,</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Transforming the collation output to survey the extents and kinds of
                        variation, and to build a digital variorum edition.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>

        <para>In the first stage, we adapt the source code from the Shelley-Godwin Archive
            (specialized TEI for the encoding of manuscript page surfaces) and from the Pennsylvania
            Electronic Edition (PAEE) (HTML 1.0 from the mid 1990s marking paragraphs and sectional
            headings) to create new forms of XML to carry predictable markers to assist in
            alignment. These new, pre-collation editions are resequenced (as when we move marginal
            annotations from the end of the XML document into their marked places as they would be
            read in the manuscript notebook). The texts from the PAEE are corrected against
            photofacsimiles of first publications of the novel in 1818 and 1831. They are also
            differently <quote>chunked</quote> than their source texts, resizing the unit file so
            that each represents an equivalent portion small enough to collate meaningfully and
            large enough that each document demonstrably aligns with the others at its start and end
            points. We prepared 33 collation units of the novel. XML matching the pre-collation
            format is prepared from OCR texts of the 1823 edition. Building from the 1818 collation
            units, we add in encoded transcriptions of Mary Shelley's hand-written edits on
                <quote>the Thomas copy</quote> of the 1818 publication.<footnote>
                <para>This is known as <quote>the Thomas copy</quote> because Mary Shelley left the
                    1818 publication containing her handwritten insertions, deletions, and comments
                    with her friend Mrs. Thomas before leaving Italy for England in 1823, following
                    Percy Shelley’s death in Lerici. The edits may have been entered at any time
                    between 1818 and 1823, and they are of interest because they indicate at an
                    early stage that Mary Shelley wanted to alter many passages in her novel, and
                    was continuing to experiment with the characterization of Victor and the
                    Creature. But they also indicate a point of divergence, since she did not have
                    access to these edits in revising the novel for its 1831 publication. A key
                    motivation for collating these editions is to attempt to compare the novel as it
                    was being revised soon after its first publication (whose bicentennial we
                    celebrate in 2018) with its later incarnation in the traditionally widely read
                    1831 edition. Another is discovering just how different the 1816 draft notebooks
                    are from the later texts. Scholars over the past forty years have oscillated
                    between the 1831 and 1818 editions as the <quote>preferred</quote> texts, but
                    there is really no single canonical version of this novel, and for that reason
                    our Variorum edition does not indicate a standard <quote>base text</quote>,
                    which is still unusual in representing scholarly editions.</para>
            </footnote></para>

        <para>Stage two weaves these surrogate editions together and transfers information from tags
            that we want to preserve for the variorum. Interacting with the angle brackets as
            patterned strings with Python, we mask several elements from the diplomatic code of the
            manuscript notebooks so that they are not processed in terms of comparison but are
            nevertheless output to preserve their distinct information. In CollateX’s
            informationally-rich XML output, these tags render as flattened text with character
            entities replacing angle brackets so as not to introduce overlap problems with its
            critical apparatus.</para>
        <para>In Stage three, we work delicately with strings that represent flattened composite of
            preserved tag information and representations of the text, using XSLT
            string-manipulation functions to construct new XML and plain text (TSV or JSON) files
            for stylometric and other analysis. We can then study term frequencies and, for example,
            where the strings associated with Percy Shelley are repeated in the later editions, and
            how many were preserved by 1831. We also build the <emphasis role="ital">standoff
                Bridge</emphasis> in TEI for the digital variorum with its pointers to multiple
            editions, as modelled in Figure 1.</para>
        <figure xml:id="variant" xreflabel="Variant">
            <title>Sample Variant</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata format="png" fileref="Bal2018variant042711.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
            <caption>
                <para>An example variant with two different readings, showing Percy Bysshe Shelley's
                    hand in the ms notebook. While the print editions of 1818, 1823, and the
                    manuscript agree (yellow reading), the print edition of 1831 introduces new text
                    (blue reading). The pointers are expressed according to the TEI XPointer Schemes
                    defined in Chapter 16 of the TEI Guidelines and are subject to change.</para>
            </caption>
        </figure>


        <para> This example shows how the stand-off collation identifies variant readings between
            texts by grouping pointers as opposed to grouping strings of text according to the
            parallel segmentation technique described in Chapter 12 of the TEI Guidelines.<footnote>
                <para>See especially the TEI P5 Guidelines, 12.2.3 and 12.2.4: <link
                        xlink:href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TC.html#TCAPPS"
                        >http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TC.html#TCAPPS</link></para>
            </footnote> The TEI offers a stand-off method for encoding variants, called
            “double-end-point-attachment”, in which variants can be encoded separately from the base
            text by specifying the start and end point of the lemma of which they are a variant.
            This allows encoders to refer to overlapping areas on the base text, but despite its
            flexibility, this method still requires choosing a base text to which anchor variant
            readings. While choosing a lemma for each variant may be necessary for a critical
            edition, it is not ideal for a variorum edition like ours that, by design, does not
            choose a base text.<footnote>
                <para>For a related example, see Viglianti, R. Music and Words: reconciling libretto
                    and score editions in the digital medium. “Ei, dem alten Herrn zoll’ ich Achtung
                    gern’”, ed. Kristina Richts and Peter Stadler, 2016, 727-755. </para>
            </footnote> Our approach, therefore, simply identifies variance and groups readings from
            multiple sources without conflating them into one document and with accommodation of
            multiple hierarchies.</para>

        <para>Though we think of XML as a stable sustainable archiving medium, the repeated
            collapsing and expansion of hierarchies in our collation process makes us consider that
            for the viability of digital textual scholarship, ordered hierarchies of content objects
            might best be designed with leveling in mind, and that building with XML may be
            optimized when it is open to transformation. Preparing diversely encoded documents for
            collation challenges us to consider inconsistent and overlapping hierarchies as a
            tractable matter for computational alignment—where alignment becomes an organizing
            principle that fractures hierarchies, chunking if not atomizing them at the level of the
            smallest meaningfully sharable semantic features.</para>

       
    </section>







    <section>
        <title>Crossing the bridges</title>
        <para><!--CALL IT STAND-OFF PARALLEL SEGMENTATION. Designed to include pointers into <link xlink:href="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/contents/ms_abinger_c56/">the Shelley-Godwin Archive edition of the manuscript notebook drafts</link> of the novel. As well, pointers to all editions that are part of the project. --></para>

        <para>Generating the stand-off parallel segmentation required processing and manipulating
            our multiple versions of TEI-encoded <emphasis role="ital">Frankenstein</emphasis> to
            locate the <quote>addresses</quote> of each varying point. This document is not,
            however, the end of the story: the bridges that it establishes are there to be crossed.
            Crossing the bridges, that is, following the pointers is not always trivial. Serious
            reasons for the somewhat limited use of stand-off in TEI include the limited support for
            resolving XPath, as well as the risk of not finding what was expected at the other end
            because of <quote>link rot</quote>, or because the target file was – even minimally –
            changed. In creating our stand-off collation, we tried to keep pointers as simple as
            possible by favoring locations expressed with XPath 1.0 over locations with string
            ranges (although the latter are unavoidable on multiple occasions). Finally, we made use
            of GitHub’s ability to obtain URLs to specific versions of files, which means that the
            files we point to are guaranteed not to change unexpectedly (although the URL itslef may
                <quote>rot</quote> and return a 404, eventually)<footnote>
                <para>See also <link
                        xlink:href="http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol5/html/Cayless01/BalisageVol5-Cayless01.html"
                        >Cayless, Hugh A., and Adam Soroka. “On Implementing string-range() for
                        TEI.” Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2010. Balisage Series
                        on Markup Technologies, vol. 5 (2010)</link></para>
            </footnote>.</para>
        <para>Having taken these precautions, our primary goal is building a web-based interactive
            variorum edition that readers can use to explore each version of the text. For example,
            one could start by reading the 1818 version of the novel; highlighted text would
            indicate the presence of a variant from another version and by clicking on it, the site
            visitor would be able to <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>choose which variant readings they wish to read and compare, and</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>change their current view and pivot to a different text or grouping of
                        texts.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>The software building this view follows links from the stand-off parallel
            segmentation to highlight text and retrieve bits of text from the other documents to be
            shown at he right place. This mode of publication adheres to well-established user
            experiences for digital editions; the fundamental difference, however, is in the
            integrity of each source document: the stand-off collation allows us to show where the
            differences are, and to retrieve them without having to modify or control the source
            documents. One can imagine an even more distributed application of this paradigm, where
            the pointers target TEI documents not owned by the project that does the pointing.
            Working with Shelley-Godwin Archive (S-GA) documents was a first experiment in this
            direction. Even though S-GA staff is directly involved in this project, we have made it
            a cornerstone of our experiment to not modify S-GA files (except the occasional typo or
            minor contribution that was sent back via a GitHub Pull Request); in short, we treated
            S-GA as an external project that we can point to but not change.</para>
        <para>Publishing the variorum is but one path that can be taken across the bridges of our
            collation. As we mentioned earlier, we kept in mind the richness of S-GA TEI documents,
            particularly regarding authorship (who wrote what) and authorial revisions. In order to
            follow a pointer to an S-GA document, we must process the full document; while it may
            seem counter-intuitive, this is an advantage because we gain access to the full context
            of the text we addresses.
            <!-- reference to Witmore's concept of addressability? http://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/text/28 -->
            This would allow us, for example, to determine and indicate in the user interface
            whether a variant reading was part of a revision by Percy Shelley, or allows us to
            perform larger scale operations to track such phenomena, which could then be plotted as
            visualizations.</para>








    </section>

</article>
