<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="balisage-1-3.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="balisage-1-3.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="balisage-proceedings-html.xsl"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0-subset Balisage-1.3">

    <title>Text Encoding and Literate Programming for a University Writing Intensive Course</title>
   <!-- <subtitle></subtitle>-->
    <info>
        <abstract>
            <para>Can learning text encoding and markup languages constitute a <quote>writing
                    intensive</quote> experience for university students? The author is developing a
                Text Encoding Fundamentals course with emphasis on text encoding as writing, as well
                as a proposal that this fulfill a major state university requirement of a
                research-oriented 300-level <quote>writing intensive</quote> or <quote>W</quote>
                course for undergraduate students. The course is specifically
                designed for those pursuing a Digital Media, Arts, and Technology major but must
                also be available to others in related disciplines as an experience in <quote>writing across the curriculum</quote>. While we may be familiar with
                arguments that coding and programming are a kind of literacy, the idea that
                developing projects with markup technologies may constitute an
                    <emphasis>intensive</emphasis> writing experience is less familiar. The
                consideration of text encoding as writing intensive may establish a call for
                teaching markup technologies more widely in a cross-disciplinary context.</para>
            <para>Not just any course introducing students to markup should be considered writing
                intensive. Arguably, a class that involves tagging exercises without project
                development and invites students to write reflectively about the experience is not
                engaging in an <emphasis>intensive</emphasis> way with the writing work we associate
                with coding in a project development context. This paper argues that a
                    <emphasis>writing intensive</emphasis> course in coding should take seriously
                the notion that coding and programming is a writing process that requires research
                and citation, algorithmic problem-solving and decision making, task management to
                organize a project team, and documentation to share the work and help others to
                build upon it. A course offering such experiences should, finally, be accessible to
                students from several disciplines, whether to a junior year English or history major
                with little to no programming experience, or a junior year computer science or
                information technology major with an interest in applied programming, unused to
                research questions that drive humanities scholarship. In presenting its case, this
                paper responds to a range of literature to evaluate the relationships among
                    <emphasis>encoding</emphasis>, <emphasis>coding</emphasis>,
                    <emphasis>programming</emphasis>, and <emphasis>writing</emphasis>.</para>
        </abstract>
        <author>
            <personname>
                <firstname>Elisa</firstname>
                <othername>E.</othername>
                <surname>Beshero-Bondar</surname>
            </personname>
            <personblurb>
                <para>Elisa Beshero-Bondar is a member of the TEI Technical Council, as well as Professor of Digital Humanities and Program Chair of Digital Media, Arts, and Technology at Penn State Erie, the Behrend College. Until June 2020, she was a professor of English Literature and Director of the Center for the Digital Text at Pitt-Greensburg which has featured a markup languages as a foundation of a curriculum in Digital Studies. Her projects investigate complex texts such as epics, plays, and multi-volume voyage logs, and involve her in experimentations with the TEI, including refining methods for computer-assisted collation of editions and probing questions of interoperability to reconcile diplomatic and critical edition encodings. She is the founder and organizer of the <link xlink:href="http://digitalmitford.org">Digital Mitford project</link> and <link xlink:href="https://digitalmitford.github.io/DigMitCS/">its usually annual coding school</link>. Her ongoing adventures with markup technologies are documented on <link xlink:href="http://newtfire.org">her development site at newtfire.org</link>. </para>
            </personblurb>
            <affiliation>
                <jobtitle>Professor of Digital Humanities</jobtitle>
                <jobtitle>Program Chair of Digital Media, Arts, and Technology</jobtitle>
                <orgname>Penn State Erie, the Behrend College</orgname>
            </affiliation>
            <email>eeb4@psu.edu</email>
        </author>
        <keywordset role="author">
            <keyword>markup</keyword>
            <keyword>writing intensive</keyword>
            <keyword>literate programming</keyword>
            <keyword>interchange</keyword>
            <keyword>code literacy</keyword>
            <keyword>general education requirement</keyword>
            <keyword>pedagogy</keyword>
            <keyword>coding across the curriculum</keyword>
            <keyword>Text Encoding Initiative</keyword>
            <keyword>TEI XML</keyword>
            <keyword>Relax NG</keyword>
            <keyword>XML family of languages</keyword>
            <keyword>XPath</keyword>
            <keyword>XSLT</keyword>
            <keyword>HTML</keyword>
        </keywordset>
    </info>
    <section>
        <title>What people say about coding, encoding, and programming as literacies</title>
       <para></para>
        
        <para>Multimodal Writing: Addressing recent trends to assign student writing compositions in digital modalities such as audio and video, Laura Giovanelli and Molly Keener observe that <quote>Well-designed pedagogy recognizes multimodal writing’s potential to foster student agency and ownership as increasingly participatory citizens where literacy means composing in a range of print and digital media, genres, and modes, where students are consumers <emphasis>and</emphasis> ethical creators.</quote> CITE: "How to talk about copyright so kids will listen, and how to listen about copyright so kids will talk" in Grace Veach, Teaching​ Information Literacy and Writing Studies : Volume 2, Upper-Level and Graduate Courses (Purdue University Press, 2019-01-15.  ProQuest ebook http://ebookcentral.proquest.com/lib/pitt-ebooks/reader.action?docID=5717973
            
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Challenging the notion of writing, and improving it</title>
        <para></para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Writing intensively and across the curriculum with markup languages</title>
        <para>The XML family of languages were designed not only to be widely accessible, but also were designed to be a vocabulary the writer controls or consults or interacts with, and requires a hierarchical structuring. It does not take very long to acquaint new coders to the rules of how to tag a document, or how to turn a <quote>plain text</quote> document into an XML document, though often people experience a little frustration with typing in the attributes or figuring what they can do with attributes. The first week or two of a class that involves markup methods can orient people to how to code something in XML, but the interesting experience of that can be when we ask students to develop their own hierarchies to organize what they are reading, and when we invite our students to try to recognize what is implicit, and find ways to use elements, attributes, or comments to make that explicit. The act of inscribing markup has been recognized (CITE KATE SINGER) as a writing process, but if it goes no further than an exercise in tagging, perhaps we should consider this something like writing a reflective paper, a response that sharpens one’s observation and critical thinking skills. In my years of teaching undergraduates to code, I notice in the first couple of weeks that certain students have difficulties with conceptualizing dependencies, or what the relationship between an element and an attribute and its value ought to be. They sometimes prepare shallow hierarchies, and instead of bundling list items together in a cluster, make a very flat tree where every line is its own entry. These students benefit from seeing more detailed markup, and also from understanding something about how the markup may be processed, how it can be used to organize and access particular kinds of information. For that reason, I have found that inviting my students to write their first markup on a recipe, one that contains an interesting variety of ingredients, measurement units, and activities, provides a very clear and easily recognizable sense of structure with lots of categories of information. [CITE Newtfire XML EX 1] So, too, does a poem, or a piece of historical correspondence. Students who have difficulty constructing dependent clauses may find the preparation of an informative, non-redundant hierarchy just as challenging. Quite frequently student beginners will take the text content of a document and repeat it in an attribute value, as for example wrapping code around a name as given in a text, and using that name in an attribute value on the element, until they receive some suggestions that they might want to use the attribute as a key for a standard identifier whenever this individual is mentioned by their various names.</para>
  <para>Learning to code the XML syntax is easy. Learning to optimize one’s preparation of XML takes a long time, takes practice, and takes application, just like learning to write good sentences and paragraphs, and learning to develop a research paper or a thesis. Just like these progressively more complex writing activities, we can identify levels of intensity in increasing applications of markup technologies, and the challenges to the thinking and communication process are remarkably similar. The increasing intensity is not simply due to learning new technologies, but rather becomes gradually more intensive in cognitive ways. The process of becoming a better reader and writer and coder and developer is also the process of becoming more adept in organizing and processing information. Writing may be easily recognizable in the practice we call mere tagging in first-time coders, but the way one becomes a better writer with markup is by learning what can be done with and made from the markup. The processes of navigating, extracting, transforming, and remixing data marked in an XML tree define the <emphasis>intensive</emphasis>  part of the writing process. When students learn only tagging and do not learn how to parse their own code, they remain unaware of what the markup makes possible, and they may often be unaware of the problems imposed by imprecision and inconsistency. They may be tagging correctly, but not in a way that communicates meaningfully or reliably. Worse yet, in becoming aware of the human unreliabilities in applying markup, they may come away with the idea that the tree structures we create are arbitrary, exert an aggressive control over a document. [CITE] This line of thinking relies on an unsustained, non-intensive engagement with marked documents and an unfortunate separation of the technologies of managing and processing XML from instruction in markup.</para>      
  <para>Just as we think of free-writing as a valuable exercise to start a first preliminary draft in a composition class, in teaching markup, a certain amount of mess and unreliability is okay as we are learning or figuring out what matters to prioritize. Often new coders introduce far more differently named elements than they really need, or that would be baffling to keep track of in a real-life project. To come to an understanding of how to code helpfully and meaningfully, a student needs to confront the problem of sharing and reproducibility—concepts parallel to the awareness of an audience emphasized in rhetoric and composition classes as a means to craft better sentences, to trim out verbosity.</para>       
   <para>Students often improve their markup dramatically when they learn to write Relax NG schema code, that creates rules for encoding. This may be a first data-modeling experience for students in a general education context, when they are called upon to think in a <quote>meta</quote> or higher order reflective way about formalizing their code, and making it possible for others to understand it and reproduce it.</para>       
        <para>
        (recipe coding)
        (recipe coding with a shared context)
        (designing a schema and of controlled vocabularies: within a project)
        (decision processes for controlled vocabularies with the TEI)
        
       DATA PREPARATION: 
       up-conversion with regular expressions: pattern recognition. Useful for all kinds of text analysis, as in stemming patterns for natural language processing. In XML, a power tool for preparing a large-sized corpus of documents. 
       
       
       XSLT: constructing templates and accounting for nodes. Deciding what can be ignored. Revisiting your decisions
        Push and pull processing
        
        XQUERY and persistent datatyping
        Encounters with marked up text get you someplace different than unmarked text, and give students a constructive experience with data curation and preparation. 
        
      DOCUMENTATION and SHARING the work: establishing a context
      When students prepare a project in markup, they are not simply writing papers to be filed in a course-specific context. They are preparing a research site and their work can often be continued by them or others. Students can be building beyond the constraints of a single semester, and even if they are not tempted to return to the project, they can leave scaffolding behind for others to continue the work or alter its direction, or retrieve the files. Awareness of the potential energy of the work they are doing can give shape to an encounter with markup languages in the course of a semester. The energy input over a course of weeks puts emphasis on preparing material that others can read and reuse. Indeed, assignments for a writing intensive experience can be constructed with attention to:
      1) reading the code and documentation of other projects, and building on it
      2) preparing documentation meant to be read by peers and professor(s) working with you, and meant to be read by others who access your code from a repository. Such documentation may include:
        * Kanban board workflow management
        * README.md files
        * task lists and issues
        * being responsible and <quote>on-call</quote> for responding to questions and assisting your teammates
            
    These are activities to do with taking responsibility for method and processes, for managing the intellectual content of a project. Studying how copyright applies to code and markup and choosing a license for sharing the work should be part of this experience. 
    Giving students access to the full set of tools in the XML arsenal and establishing both immediate (in-semester) short-range and long-range possibilities for their work will introduce students from any background to the power of markup languages and with the experience of writing to form and connect with communities of practice. This cannot fail to be a professionalizing experience. Even in developing projects that are not successful, there will be opportunities to recognize in failures what to document, how to redo the work differently, how another group might start over—the project-oriented awareness gives space for documentation to <quote>sunset</quote> the work. Whether or not students go on to use markup again after the course is over, they will have engaged with a powerful form of writing that marks up, investigates, curates, propagates, and conserves textual data. This is the very definition of a writing-intensive experience that is both professionalizing and cross-disciplinary in its reach. 

Monitoring git commit messages and documentation 
        
        (documentation, XML Comments, git commits, methodology pages, sharing the work with others)
        (research in the field: referencing is connecting and networking)
        
Teaching outside the Writing/Learning/Content Management System
To this English professor and self-professed markup geek who was learning HTML in the 1990s, it is distinctly strange to read the language of educational technology specialists who seek ways gently to introduce faculty to <quote>teaching with technology</quote>. In these contexts, classes like <quote>Writing for the Web</quote> are about writing for Wix or Wordpress templates, which provide limited and little-investigated critical access to the code layer. <quote>Teaching with technology</quote> seems to mean working within a management system that facilitates digital submission of documents and return of grades and permits push notifications so faculty and students maintain asynchronous contact through a semester. 

How hard is this for Humanities faculty to learn? 
Faculty workshops and training can provide it, but it is not often offered, and perhaps we need to overcome a presumption that faculty will not be interested in the material. Where do we markup practitioners imagine that we find an audience for instructional materials? Who should be learning these technologies? Can this be treated not <emphasis>only</emphasis> as a restricted technological preserve, but as an encounter with what digital texts can be made of, as a component of digital literacy for humanities faculty and graduate programs? Can we encourage and incentivize the learning, teaching, and sharing of these technologies? The author learned enough of a foundation in a range of languages in a 15-week semester thanks to the existence of a course taught by David J. Birnbaum in the University of Pittsburgh’s Honors College program CITE, and she learned alongside a group of undergraduates, working in teams on semester projects as described in this paper. While she took the course to learn how to develop a digital edition project, she exited with the basis for developing new courses and imagining new ways of working on projects with students. Other faculty at Pitt and Pitt-Greensburg have lit their torches from the same pedagogical fires, and we are aware of faculty at UVic, U of Maryland, and Vanderbilt (just to name a few) who teach humanities students to engage with a range of XML technologies. 

Teaching Markup Languages during a Pandemic
Teaching a writing-intensive course in markup modalities offers little distress for adaptation to a remote learning environment, as we had to do recently after the university closed down face-to-face classes. This kind of class works for connecting synchronously OR asynchronously. It was much easier to continue the management of a course based on markup technologies in which students had been trained to work with project management tools and to be writing and sharing their documentation in GitHub repositories and over Slack channels than to retool one in which in-class daily discussion and traditional kinds of assignments prevailed. The digital modalities organizing our class were lively enough that the coding class might properly be recognized as <quote>flipped</quote>, in which most of the learning was already taking place in an applied context outside of class, while student and faculty class meetings reviewed content all together, to learn how to interact with an unfamiliar interface or to review issues students are having or help address something that is not working. 
        </para>
    </section>

</article>
